Guide to the Manchester Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Albums, 1697/98 Feb 8; Series I
  - The E of M to the Earl of Jersey, suggesting the expediency of an interview with the King at Loo. (Printed, with some variations, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 179) Paris, 1700 Jul 31 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - M. Hervart to the E of M, informing him that the Swiss Cantons were contriving to gain time before giving an answer on the Guarantee of the treaty of Partition, etc. (In French. A translation of the chief part is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 180) Berne [Bern], 1700 Aug 1 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - James Vernon to the E of M, on the various political topics of the day. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 193) Whitehall, 1700 Aug 5 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - James Cressett to the E of M, expressing hopes that a just and reasonable peace might be signed at the Hague, and concluding thus: "I have personell as well as politick reasons to lang for peace, for no dog can be more tyr'd with bearbaiting than I am." (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 184) Hamburg, 1700 Aug 6 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - The E of M to the Lord Chamberlain [Earl of Jersey], mentioning an enclosure, and touching very briefly on conversations with M. de Torcy respecting the Partition Treaty, and the views of Portugal on the subject. "The only discourse we have here is bombarding the Danes," he says; "it is certain nothing else will do." Paris, 1700 Aug 7 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - James Cressett to the E of M, announcing that a despatch had been sent to the King with news of a successful landing of Swedish forces near Elsinore. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 186) Hamburg, 1700 Aug 9 (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - Alexander Stanhope to the E of M on Northern affairs, and stating that Riga was threatened by the King of Poland. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 189) The Hague, 1700 Aug 12 (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - James Cressett to the E of M on affairs and prospects in the North. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 190) Hamburg, 1700 Aug 13 (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - Paul Methuen to the E of M, announcing that a Treaty of Guarantee (relating to the Partition Treaty) had been signed on behalf of the King of Portugal. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 192) Lisbon, 1700 Aug 15/18 (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - M. Hervart to the E of M, on the attitude of the Swiss with regard to the Partition Treaty. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 194) Berne [Bern], 1700 Aug 7/17 (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - R, Sutton to the E of M, announcing that the Emperor had definitely refused to accede to the Partition Treaty. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 194) Neustadt, 1700 Aug 17 (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - William Blathwayt to the E of M, expressing a belief that the Treaty to be signed within a few hours near Segeberg would put an end to hostilities in the North. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 198) Loo, 1700 Aug 20 (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - James Cressett to the E of M, announcing the signature of a Treaty of Peace at Travendal. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 199) Segeberg, 1700 Aug 20 (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - William Blathwayt to the E of M, announcing the conclusion of the peace in the North, and mentioning an enclosure in which the principal points were set forth. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 199) Loo, 1700 Aug 22 (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - James Cressett to the E of M, sending a copy of a despatch to Mr. Blathwayt. In the latter are given some particulars relating to the manner in which the Treaty of Travendal was concluded, and mention is made of an "Act signed sub spe ratificationis." (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 200) Hamburg, 1700 Aug 24 (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - William Blathwayt to the E of M, instructing him to make complaint to M. de Torcy respecting the arrest of Mr. Chetwynd at Valenciennes as a breach of the privilege of Foreign Ministers. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 201) Loo, 1700 Aug 22 (Box 4, Folder 75)
  - J. Robinson to the E of M on the Treaty of Travendal, the renewed menace of the Danes, and the slowness of the Swedish Court in acceding to the Partition Treaty. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 205) Helsingborg, 1700 Aug 25 (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - Postscript to a letter from J. Robethon to [the E of M], on the religious difficulties in Orange and the case of M. Blisson, who was anxious to pass into Holland. It is in reply to a letter from the Earl dated Jan. 29. (In French) (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - The E of M to the Lord Chamberlain [Earl of Jersey], on the refusal of the Emperor to accede to the Partition Treaty, and on the case of Count Boscelli [Bosselli], on which instructions are requested. (Draft. Printed, with some variations, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 202) Paris, 1700 Aug 27 (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - William Blathwayt to the E of M on Mr. Chetwynd's arrest, on the Emperor and the Treaty of Partition, and on affairs in the North. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 203) Loo, 1700 Sep 3 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - M. Hervart to the E of M, announcing that the Diet of the Cantons would be held on the 19th of the same month, for the consideration of the Partition Treaty. He also enquires in what manner it would be right for him to go into mourning for the Duke of Gloucester. (In French.) Berne [Bern], 1700 Sep 4 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - William Blathwayt to the E of M, instructing him to make the King of France acquainted with the desire of the English that there should be a pacification between Sweden and Poland. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 204) Loo, 1700 Sep 5 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - James Cressett to the E of M, sending a copy of a letter "to Court," in which he recommends the demolition of the Hittler fort in the Elbe - a question submitted to the arbitrage of England, France, and Holland. (printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 207) Hamburg, 1700 Sep 10 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - James Cressett to the E of M, announcing his departure from Hamburg to press the Court of Lunenburg to accede to the Partition Treaty. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 210) Hamburg, 1700 Sep 20 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - M. Schonenberg to the E of M, on the attitude of Spain in respect of the admission of foreign troops into the Italian dominions, and on dissentions concerning the Spanish succession. (In French. A translation of the principal part is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 211) Madrid, 1700 Sep 23 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - The E of M to the lord Chamberlain [Earl of Jersey], mentioning enclosure from M. Schonenberg, and asking for instructions respecting the mode of notifying the death of the Duke of Gloucester at the French Court, etc. (Draft. The principal part is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 211) Paris, 1700 Sep 24 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - The E of M to Mr. Stanhope, mentioning enclosures, of which one was from M. Schonenberg. One for Mr. Blathwayt should not be delayed. They were supposed to refer to the entry of Imperial troops into Spanish territory in Italy. (Copy) Paris, 1700 Sep 25 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - On the same paper is a copy of a letter to Mr. Blathwayt, also mentioning enclosures., 1700 Sep 25 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - The E of M to the Lord Chamberlain [Earl of Jersey], asking what were the King's intentions with respect to the appointment of Exempt of the Guards, for which he wished to recommend an officer. He also mentions a report that the Elector of Brandenburg was to be declared King of Prussia upon condition of furnishing 8,000 men to the Emperor against Italy. (Draft. Printed, with some variations, and without the part relating to patronage, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 209) Paris, 1700 Sep 17 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - M. Hervart to the E of M, announcing that the Swiss had declined to accede to the Partition Treaty. (In French. A translation is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 213) Soleure, 1700 Sep 29 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - The E of M to M. Schonenberg, expressing thanks for information respecting the Spanish Court, and a belief that the good understanding between France and England would continue. (Draft, in French. A translation is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 214) Paris, 1700 Oct 3 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - The E of M to Mr. Methuen, announcing that the Electors of Hanover and Brandenburg would shortly meet the King at the Hague, and that there was a probability of the enlargement of the Act for the settlement of the English Crown. (Draft. Printed, with some variations, in Cole's memoirs, p. 214) Paris, 1700 Oct 3 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - James Cressett to the E of M, giving some details of the manner in which he had "carried his pack of Spanish merchandise [the Partition Treaty] about with him from Court to Court, "and yet did not see many customers fond of it." (Six pages. Printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 214) Zell, 1700 Oct 4 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - M. Robethon to the E of M, giving instructions respecting the delivery of an "ordonnance visée" to the bearer of the King's order and touching upon various other matters affecting the principality of Orange. (In French. A translation is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 216) Loo, 1700 Oct 6 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - James Vernon to the E of M, mentioning briefly Sir Charles Duncombe and the Court of Aldermen, Lord Bradford's illness, etc, and asking for copies of accounts (about to be reprinted by the Court of St. Germains) of the death of King Charles, and the Duchess of York in the Catholic Faith. Whitehall, 1700 Oct 7 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Beginning of an unfinished and undirected letter written by the E of M, on the affairs of Orange. (In French) Paris, 1700 Oct 11 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - The E of M to Mr. Blathwayt on the reception, by the French King, of the notification of the death of the Duke of Gloucester. (Draft. Printed, with some variations, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 218), 1700 Oct 11 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - The E of M to Mr. Stanhope, on the expected death of the King of Spain, and its probable consequences. (Draft. Printed, with some variations, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 220), 1700 Oct 11 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - The E of M to the Lord Chamberlain [Earl of Jersey] on the expected death of the King of Spain, the attitude of the Emperor, the augmentation of the French army, the movements of the French Navy, etc. (Draft, pp. 7. Printed with some variations, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 218) Paris, 1700 Oct 11 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Alexander Stanhope to the E of M, giving news of the march of the Czar to the assistance of the King of Poland against the Swedes, and other matters. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 221) The Hague, 1700 Oct 14 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - James Vernon to the E of M, on the expected arrival of the King of England and other topics. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 229) Whitehall, 1700 Oct 14 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - The E of M to Mr. Blathwayt, expressing his belief that the King of France was anxious to co-operate with the King of England in bringing the King of Poland and the Czar to terms of peace with Sweden, and announcing that the Elector of Brandenburg contradicted the report that he had engaged to support the Emperor with troops. (Draft, pp. 5. Printed, with some variations, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 222) Fontainebleau, 1700 Oct 16 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - The E of M to Mr. Blathwayt, on various reports from Spain, etc. (Draft. Printed, with some variations, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 223) Fontainebleau, 1700 Oct 17 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - The E of M to Mr. Stanhope, mentioning some reports from Spain, the Polish difficulty, etc. (Draft. Printed, with some variations, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 222) Fontainebleau, 1700 Oct 17 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - The E of M to some French official, on the case of Mr. Hart, who had been delayed in France by the attempt of a woman to extort money from him. The Earl was reluctant to speak to M. de Torcy on the subject. (Draft. In French), 1700 Oct 18 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - The E of M to Mr. Stanhope, stating that he had no further news. (Draft) Fontainebleau, 1700 Oct 21 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - The E of M to Mr. Blathwayt, on the attitude of the Emperor, and on the interpretation of the treaty of Oliva, by the Polish Envoy, with respect to the Courland forts. (Draft. Printed, with some variations, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 224) Fontainebleau, 1700 Oct 21 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - James Cressett to the E of M, giving a copy of a letter to Mr. Blathwayt on the continuance of dissentions in the North. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 225), 1700 Oct 21 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - The E of M to Mr. Cressett, touching briefly on various points of European politics. (Draft. Printed, with some variations, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 225) Fontainebleau, 1700 Oct 21 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - The E of M to Mr. Stanhope, mentioning enclosures to the Lord Chamberlain and Mr. Blathwayt. (Draft. Printed, with some variations, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 229), 1700 Oct 24 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - James Vernon to the E of M, instructing him not to encourage the Danes in any hopes of keeping the Hittler fort, and giving some particulars of home affairs. (Printed, with the variation of "Hether" for "Hittler," in Cole's Memoirs, p. 233) Hampton Court, 1700 Oct 21 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - M. Schonenberg to the E of M, informing him that the King of Spain, who in the extremity of his illness had been persuaded to sign a will in favour of the second son of the Dauphin, had, upon his recovery, shown great indignation against the ministers who had advised him. (In French. A translation is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p 226) Madrid, 1700 Oct 21 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - M. Schonenberg to the E of M, informing him that the King of Spain had signed another will or codicil, of which the purport was kept secret, but in which it was supposed that he had named the Archduke Charles of Austria his successor. (In French. A translation of a portion only is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 228) Madrid, 1700 Oct 22 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Alexander Stanhope to [the E of M], expressing a belief that the King of Poland was willing to make peace with Sweden, etc. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 227) The Hague, 1700 Oct 22 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - William Blathwayt to the E of M, mentioning an enclosure which would show what were his Majesty's "intended motions," etc. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 228) The Hague, 1700 Oct 11/22 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - The E of M to the Lord Chamberlain [Earl of Jersey] on Spanish affairs, military movements of the French, etc. (Draft. Printd, with some variations, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 228) Fontainebleau, 1700 Oct 24 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - The E of M to Mr. Montagu, expressing anxiety about the next Session of Parliament, and repeating some details given in other letters. (Draft) Fontainebleau, 1700 Oct 25 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - H. Greg to the E of M, on the delay of the Danish King to accede to the Partition Treaty, and various affairs in the North. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 230) Copenhagen, 1700 Oct 15/26 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - R. Sutton to the E of M on the reluctance of the Emperor to accede to the Partition Treaty, with details, at some length, respecting the position and resources of the Empire. (6 pages. Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 231) Vienna, 1700 Oct 26 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - The Earl of Jersey to the E of M, giving instructions respecting proposed modifications of the Treaty of Partition, in favour of the Duke of Savoy. (Partly in cipher, deciphered. Printed, as deciphered, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 238) Whitehall, 1700 Oct 28 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - M. Schonenberg to the E of M, announcing that the King of Spain had had an alarming relapse. (In French. A translation is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 232) Madrid, 1700 Oct 27 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - James Vernon to the E of M, instructing him to bring to the notice of M. de Torcy certain practices of the Indians sanctioned by the Governor of Canada, and giving an account of the trial of 90 French pirates at the Admiralty Sessions, etc. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 238) Whitehall, 1700 Oct 28 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - M. Schonenberg to the E of M, informing him that the King of Spain was not expected to live through the night, and that certain powers had been given to Cardinal Portocarrero. (In French. A translation is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 233) Madrid, 1700 Oct 31 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - M. Blisson to the E of M, requesting the latter to interest himself on behalf of M. Blisson who was unable to obtain a passport, who justified his past conduct, and hoped he would not be abandoned after displaying much zeal and assiduity. (In French) Orange, 1700 Nov 1 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - James Vernon to the E of M, mentioning enclosure of the Secret Article by which the Emperor was allowed two months after the death of the King of Spain to decide whether he would accede to the Partition Treaty. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 243) Whitehall, 1700 Nov 2 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - The E of M to the Lord Chamberlain [Earl of Jersey] on Spanish affairs: to the effect that the French King was satisfied with the mode of partition but would consent to any reasonable alteration of the Treaty, if desired by the King of England. (Draft. Printed, with some variations and ommisions, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 234) Paris, 1700 Nov 3 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Part of an undirected letter, in the handwriting of the E of M, on Spanish affairs, the relations of "the Elector" with the Emperor, etc. (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Paul Methuen to the E of M, announcing that the King of Portugal had signed his Act of Accession to the Partition Treaty. (Printed, Cole's Memoirs, p. 235) Lisbon, 1700 Nov 4 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - James Vernon to the E of M, informing him that the King did not consider it expedient to make any change in the Partition Treaty until two months had elapsed after notification of the death of the King of Spain to the Emperor. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 244) Whitehall, 1700 Nov 4 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - M. Schonenberg to the E of M, mentioning enclosure of a packet for His Majesty, and announcing that upon the death of the King of Spain it was found that the Duc d'Anjou had been named successor by will. Other details are given, both of the will, and of the post mortem examination of the body of the King of Spain. (In French. A translation is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 235) Madrid, 1700 Nov 4 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - The E of M to M. de Lubières on the affairs of Orange, and expressing hopes of obtaining a passport for M. Blisson. (Draft in French. A translation is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 236) Paris, 1700 Nov 5 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - James Cressett to the E of M, giving a copy of a despatch to Mr. Secretary Vernon on Northern affairs, and on the probability of Danish troops entering Saxony. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 237) Zell, 1700 Nov 5 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Alexander Stanhope to the E of M on the interpretation of the Treaty of Travendal, and difficulties anticipated from the march of Danish troops into Saxony. (The principal part is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 241) The Hague, 1700 Nov 11 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - M. Schonenberg to the E of M, mentioning enclosure for the King, and giving an account of the attitude of the Queen Dowager of Spain, and the movements of French troops. (In French. A translation is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 245) Madrid, 1700 Nov 18 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - James Vernon to the E of M on the Partition Treaty, and on the project for placing a French Prince on the throne of Spain. (Partly in cipher, with decipher on fly-leaf. Printed, with some variations, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 248) Whitehall, 1700 Nov 18 (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - James Cressett to the E of M, announcing the march of the Danes towards Saxony, and of the Swedes towards Wismar, and expressing an opinion that the conjuncture was important. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 247) Hanover, 1700 Nov 26 (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - M. Schonenberg to the E of M, announcing the proclamation of the Duc d'Anjou as Phillip V, King of Spain, and giving various details of the situation. (In French. A translation of the greater part is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 255) Madrid, 1700 Dec 2 (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - The E of M to Mr. Stanhope, announcing the expected departure of the Duc d'Anjou for Spain, and expressing fears that "the affairs of Europe were in a very ill condition." (Draft. Printed, with some variations, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 255) Paris, 1700 Dec 3 (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Project of treaty for the settlement of the affairs of Orange as sent to M. Vryberge by Lord Portland. (In French), 1700 Dec 5/15 (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - J. Robinson to the E of M, giving a long account of the victory of the Swedes over the Muscovites. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 266) Stockholm, 1700 Dec 8 (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - James Vernon to the E of M, directing him forward to an enclosed letter containing a copy of the instructions given to Dr. Aglionby who had been appointed to carry his Majesty's answer to a letter received from the Regency of Spain. The Earl was to forward this enclosure to M. Schonenberg as a precaution against the possible detention of Dr. Aglionby by adverse winds. Particulars are also given of a conversation Mr. Secretary Vernon and M. Tallard, chiefly on affairs connected with Spain. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 267) Whitehall, 1700 Dec 10 (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Alexander Stanhope to the E of M, announcing that the States had despatched their preliminary answer to the French King (in which they asked for time to arrive at a decision on matters connected with the Spanish succession) and expressing an opinion that it would be premature to take any action with respect to the Dutch troops in Flanders. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 259) The Hague, 1700 Dec 10 (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - Matthew Prior to the E of M on the probability of a new Parliament being summoned, and on political prospects in general. (6 pages. Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 269) Whitehall, 1700 Dec 10 (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - James Vernon to the E of M, giving some particulars of M. Tallard's interview with the King, and of the movements of Meers and Captain Magrath. (Partly in cipher, deciphered on fly-leaf. Nearly all printed, as deciphered, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 270) Whitehall, 1700 Dec 12 (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - M. Schonenberg to the E of M, giving an account of the measures, military and otherwise, adopted by the Court of Madrid, with reflections upon the weakness of Spain. (In French. A translation of the principal part is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 263) Madrid, 1700 Dec 16 (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - James Cressett to the E of M, giving a copy of a letter to Sir Charles Hedges on the politics of Brunswick, Zell, Hanover, etc. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 263) Zell, 1700 Dec 17 (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - J. Robethon to the E of M on the affairs of the Principality of Orange. (In French. A translation is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 265) Hampton Court, 1700 Dec 8/19 (Box 5, Folder 68)
  - The E of M to Lord Halifax [late Mr. Montagu], complaining that his expenses had not been paid, and asking Lord Halifax to mention the matter to the E of J, who had more interest than ever with the King, and who had named the new Secretary. "I cannot," he says, "comprehend what we are doing, and what measures we intend to take with France." He wished to have "some light into affairs at home, and how people stood affected." Paris, 1700 Dec 19 (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - The Earl of Albemarle to M. Schuylenbourg, directing him to give the necessary order to the King's Treasurer at Orange for an extra payment of 2,000 francs per annum to M. Lubières, the King's commandant there. (Copy. In French. A translation is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 266) Hampton Court, 1700 Dec 20 (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - S. Edwin to the E of M on various social topics, with a mention of the promotion of Newton to be Master of the Mint. Mr. Montagu being "out of the Treasury" was "all over pleasure and making his house as fine as possible to entertain the ladies: particularly the bathing room is to be mightily finished with a fine field bed.", 1699 Dec 25 (Box 5, Folder 71)